Finding Aid for LaVerne Jones Collection
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
LaVerne Jones Collection 1878-1966 1900-1944
Jones, LaVerne
1.4 linear feet (in 2 boxes)
2014073 Aa 2
LaVerne Jones was an employee of the Michigan Bell Telephone Company. The materials include board of directors minutes, correspondence, publications, reports, maps, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material was donated by Eleanor Jones (donor no. 10792 ) in June 2012.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
While a Michigan Bell Telephone Company was created in 1881, the Michigan Bell Telephone Company whose records are contained in this collection was founded in 1904, when a group led by Norman Harris of Chicago formed the Michigan State Telephone Company with headquarters in Detroit. The name changed to Michigan Bell Telephone Company in 1924 (Box 1, Miscellaneous). The company held licensing contracts with AT&T and eventually controlled all AT&T lines in Michigan. After passage of the 1921 Graham Act made it easier for AT&T and its subsidiaries to acquire independent telephone companies, Michigan Bell controlled over eighty percent of the total phone lines in the state. The introduction of direct dialing in the 1950s allowed for the rapid expansion of service occurring in the 1960s and 1970s. Following the ruling of an antitrust lawsuit in 1984, Michigan Bell was divested from AT&T and became part of the regional holding company Ameritech.
The LaVerne Jones Collection contains records documenting the Michigan Bell Telephone Company's history, primarily in the first half of the twentieth century. The records contain correspondence, publications, reports, maps, photographic materials, and several miscellaneous documents.
Correspondence includes topics such as audits, stock, legal issues, rate controversies, organizational changes, and government nationalization of the telephone system in 1918-1919. Much of the correspondence is addressed to or signed by Mr. A. von Schlegell, general manager.
Prominent publications include telephone directories at the state, county, and local levels; a history of the telephone in Michigan; several issues of "The Michigan Bell" magazine; an engineering bulletin; and a manual of telephone services.
Reports consist of annual company reports, topical reports such as one on inventory and appraisal, and a large work entitled "Histories of Michigan Bell Telephone Company Exchanges."
Miscellaneous records include research documents relating to the company's formation, early history, and organizational structure as well as board of directors minutes from the Valley Home Telephone Company at the time it was acquired by Michigan Bell in 1922.
The maps consist primarily of base maps which are marked with telephone lines and proposed extensions of lines, as well as boundaries of areas serviced by Michigan Bell. Mapped areas include Detroit, Grand Rapids, Kalamazoo, Benton Harbor, and the Bay City-Saginaw area, as well as the state of Michigan as a whole
Photographic materials include both prints and negatives and feature mostly company facilities and equipment such as transformers and switchboards. There is also a photo celebrating the consolidation of the Michigan State Telephone Company and the Valley Home Telephone Company in 1922. Also contained in this collection are photos of telephone poles being transported by train and a Michigan central train wreck.
Subjects:
Michigan Bell Telephone Company.; Telephone companies--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- LaVerne Jones Collection
  - Correspondence
    - 1899 (Box 1)
    - 1900-1909, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1910-1919, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 1920-1929 (Box 1)
    - 1930-1939 (Box 1)
    - 1940-1943 (Box 1)
  - Publications
    - Articles, 1917 (Box 1)
    - Booklets/Leaflets, 1899-1918, undated (Box 1)
    - Bulletins, 1921 (Box 1)
    - Directories, 1878-1949 (Box 1)
    - "A History of Michigan in Paintings," 1966 (Box 1)
    - "History of the Telephone in Michigan," circa 1964 (Box 1)
    - Manual of Telephone Services, 1935, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - "The Michigan Bell," 1953, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1960-1966, undated (Box 1)
    - Programs, 1919 undated (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - Annual, 1904-1916 (Box 1)
    - "Histories of Michigan Bell Telephone Company Exchanges," undated, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Topical, 1915-1919 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2)
  - Maps, 1899-1944, undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Photographic Materials
    - Negatives, 1925 undated (Box 2)
    - Prints, 1913-1966, undated (Box 2)